Chapter 1: Apples to Apples

Sorting is the act of arranging items into a logical orger. That said, in order to know which item goes in front of the other, they much be compared. This means that the first step in sorting is making sure the items you want to sort can be compared.

In Rust, we can only compare items of the same type. For example, consider the comparision of 1 > 'a'. 1 is a number and 'a' is a character. They are not the same type, which means that they cannot be compared.

Example 1.1

println!("{} > {} = {}", 1, 'a', 1 > 'a');

Output 1.1

error[E0308]: mismatched types
 --> examples/example1-1.rs:2:42
  |
2 |     println!("{} > {} = {}", 1, 'a', 1 > 'a');
  |                                          ^^^ expected integer, found `char`

error[E0277]: can't compare `{integer}` with `char`
 --> examples/example1-1.rs:2:40
  |
2 |     println!("{} > {} = {}", 1, 'a', 1 > 'a');
  |                                        ^ no implementation for `{integer} < char` and `{integer} > char`

1 and 2 are both numbers, but Rust has different types of numbers. So, if 1 is of type u8 and 2 is of type i32, then we still cannot compare them.

Example 1.2

let one: u8 = 1;
let two: i32 = 2;

println!("{} > {} = {}", one, two, one > two);

Output 1.2

error[E0308]: mismatched types
 --> examples/example1-2.rs:5:46
  |
5 |     println!("{} > {} = {}", one, two, one > two);
  |                                        ---   ^^^ expected `u8`, found `i32`
  |                                        |
  |                                        expected because this is `u8`
  |
help: you can convert `one` from `u8` to `i32`, matching the type of `two`
  |
5 |     println!("{} > {} = {}", one, two, i32::from(one) > two);
  |                                        ++++++++++   +

It is only when 1 and 2 are of the same type that we can compare them.

Example 1.3

let one: u8 = 1;
let two: u8 = 2;
println!("{} > {} = {}", one, two, one > two);

Output 1.3

1 > 2 = false

For simple examples, we do not have to specify the type because Rust has type inference, which means, in the absense of an explicit type, the compilier will make an educated guess as to which type to use. Coming back the our comparison of 1 > 2, the compilier will note that these numbers are being compared and set them to be the same type

Example 1.4

let one = 1;
let two = 2;

println!("{} > {} = {}", one, two, one > two);

Output 1.4

1 > 2 = false

Chapter 2. Line Them Up

Once you know that your items are comparable, you can then put them into a Vector and use the Vector's sort method to order them. The sort method will re-arrange the items within the Vector. This implies that the Vector will be modified, which means that the Vector must be mutable.

Example 2.1

let mut list = vec![3,2,5,1,6,7,8,0,9,4];
list.sort();
		      
println!("{:?}", list);

Output 2.1

[0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9]

In the above example, we use {:?} instead of {} to print out the list because {} is used for objects that implement the Display Trait. Vectors do not implement the Display Trait, but they do implement the Debug Trait, which means that their debug representation that can be printed. The :? tells the formatter to print out the debug representation of the object.

Another way to sort a Vector is to use the sort_by method. This method has the following function signature:

Function Signature Snippet

pub fn sort_by<F>(&mut self, mut compare: F)
    where
        F: FnMut(&T, &T) -> Ordering,

The sort_by function takes an argument called compare that is, itself, a function. The compare function accepts references of two items that are of the same type and returns a variant of the Ordering Enum. The purpose of this function is to compare two items. The returned value (Ordering Enum) will let us know if item A is less than (Ordering::Less), greater than (Ordering::Greater) or equal to (Ordering::Equal) item B.

Example 2.2

let mut list = vec![3,2,5,1,6,7,8,0,9,4];
list.sort_by(|a, b| a.cmp(b));
			
println!("{:?}", list);

Output 2.2

[0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9]

In the above example, we pass the closure |a, b| a.cmp(b) to the sort_by method. This closure takes two parameters; a and b. Then, in the function body, use the cmp method to compare a to b. The cmp method returns a variant of the Ordering Enum.

Where did the cmp method come from?

In order to sort a list, you must be able to compare the items of that list, but how do you know if the items are comparable? I've previously mentioned that the items must have the same type, but that is only part of the answer. The full answer is that the items have to be of the same type and that type must implement the Ord Trait, which is a trait that gaurentees that items of the same type are comparable. The existence of the cmp method is a result of implementing the Ord Trait. An example of the Ord Trait being required for functions that compare items when sorting can be seen in the function signature of Vec's sort method:

Function Signature Snippet

impl<T> [T] {
...
pub fn sort(&mut self)
    where
        T: Ord,
...

From the snippet of Vector's sort method, we see that, in order to use the sort method, T, which represents the type of the elements of the list, has to implement the Ord Trait. This means that all of our previous examples that have successfully used the sort method were able to do so because all of the elements had the same type and that type implemented the Ord Trait.

Chapter 3: Logical Arrangements

The power of the Ordering Enum is in the usage of its API and its variants. For example, if you want to sort a Vector of numbers in ascending order, we can accomplish this with the sort method by calling it with no arguements, but we can also accomplish this with the sort_by method by passing in the closure |a, b| a.cmp(b).

Example 3.1

let mut list_1 = [6,5,7,4,8,2,9,1,3,0];
let mut list_2 = [6,5,7,4,8,2,9,1,3,0];

list_1.sort();

list_2.sort_by(|a, b| a.cmp(b));

assert_eq!(list_1, list_2);

If we wanted to sort the numbers into descending order, we cannot directly do this with the sort method. We could call sort on a list and then call reverse to give us the correct ordering, but, in doing so, we are not acheiving the correct ordering via sorting. With the sort_by method, we have move options. Yes, we could sort the Vector in ascending order and then call reverse on it, but we can also call reverse on the result of the individual comparisons from the cmp method. This is because cmp returns a variant of the Ordering Enum, and the Ordering Enum has a reverse method that allows you to reverse the result of the comparision. In other words, Ordering::Less, becomes Ordering::Greater, Ordering::Greater becomes Ordering::Less while Ordering::Equal stays the same. This means that if we use sort_by to sort the list in decending order, we will acheive the correct arrangement of elements via the sorting process and without any need of any extra operatons.

Example 3.2

let mut list_1 = [6,5,7,4,8,2,9,1,3,0];
let mut list_2 = [6,5,7,4,8,2,9,1,3,0];

list_1.sort();
list_1.reverse();

list_2.sort_by(|a, b| a.cmp(b).reverse());

assert_eq!(list_1, list_2);

What if we wanted to arrange all of the numbers in ascending order and have all of the odd numbers appear before all of the even numbers? We know we cannot do this with the sort method because we have no way of telling it how to partition our elements into groups of numbers, but we can do this with the sort_by method. We accomplish this by writing a function that determines if a or b is odd, and, if only one of them is odd, we give that one priority. Keeping the default behavior in mind in which the item of least value gets placed in front, we give odd numbers priority over even numbers by making sure we always report that the odd number is less than the even number.

Example 3.3

use std::cmp::Ordering;

fn main() {
    let mut list: Vec<i32> = vec![3, 2, 5, 1, 6, 7, 8, 0, 9, 4];

    list.sort_by(|a, b| {
        let a_is_odd = a.abs() % 2 == 1;
        let b_is_odd = b.abs() % 2 == 1;

        if a_is_odd && b_is_odd {
            a.cmp(b)
        } else if a_is_odd {
            Ordering::Less
        } else if b_is_odd {
            Ordering::Greater
        } else {
            a.cmp(b)
        }
    });

    println!("{:?}", list);
}

Output 3.3

[1, 3, 5, 7, 9, 0, 2, 4, 6, 8]

In the above example, our closure function checks to see if a is odd and if b is odd. If both a and b are odd (or even), then we can do a regular comparision between a and b because niether of them have priority over the other. If a is odd and b is even, we need to report that a is less than b so that a always gets placed in front of b. If b is odd and a is even, then we report that a is greater than b so that b can always be placed in front of a.

The end result of passing this closure function to our sort_by method is that all of the odd numbers are placed in front of all of the even numbers and the odd numbers and the even numbers, within their respective groups, are arranged in ascending order.

Chapter 4. My Sorting Options

We have introduced the sort and sort_by methods, but there is another method called sort_by_key that we can use as well. Here is the function signature:

Function Signature Snippet

impl<T> [T] {
...
pub fn sort_by_key<K, F>(&mut self, mut f: F)
    where
        F: FnMut(&T) -> K,
        K: Ord,
...

sort_by_key method takes in a function f that takes an element from the list and returns a value of type K where type K implements the Ord Trait. Comparing this method to sort and sort_by, we see that:

The elements of the list do not have to implement the Ord Trait (This is a requirement for sort).
The function passed in only takes a single parameter (The function passed into sort_by takes 2 parameters).
The return value of the function must implement the Ord Trait (The return value of the sort_by method is a variant of the Ordering Enum).

Point 2 tells us that the sort_by_key method is not used to compare elements in the list. Knowing that being able to compare elements in a list is a requirement for sorting, points 1 and 3 tell us that sort_by_key will return values that will later be used to sort the list. For example, if you wanted to sort the vector of [-10, -7, -3, 0, 3, 7, 10] by the values returned after applying the function x mod 7, you can do that with the sort_by_key method.

Example 4.1

fn main(){
    let mut list: Vec<i32> = vec![-10, -7, -3, 0, 3, 7, 10];
    list.sort_by_key(|x| x.rem_euclid(7));
	
    println!("{:?}", list);
}

Output 4.1

[-7, 0, 7, 3, 10, -10, -3]

In this example, we used the rem_euclid to compute the value of x mod 7 where x is an element of the list. x mod 7 gives us a list of [4, 0, 4, 0, 3, 0, 3], which is then sorted, and then the returned values are replaced with their original inputs.

Unstable Sort

One aspect of sorting that we have not questioned is what should happen when multiple elements in a list are considered equal. For example, consider the list [one, two, also_one, also_two] where one and also_one equal 1 and two and also_two equal 2. If we were to sort this list, then, technically speaking, there are 4 valid combinations:

Valid Combinations

[one, also_one, two, also_two]
[one, also_one, also_two, two]
[also_one, one, two, also_two]
[also_one, one, also_two, two]

Example 4.2

let one = 1;
let also_one = 1;
let two = 2;
let also_two = 2;

let list_1 = vec![one, also_one, two, also_two];
let list_2 = vec![also_one, one, also_two, two];

println!("{:?} == {:?} = {}", list_1, list_2, list_1 == list_2);

Output 4.2

[1, 1, 2, 2] == [1, 1, 2, 2] = true

When comparing two variations of our sorted list, we see that they are equal. That said, having multiple possible arrangements is not always ideal. For that reason, we have two types of sorts; unstable sort and stable sort.

Unstable sort is sorting where there is no definitive order given to elements that are considered equal. In theory, this gives rise to the situation where the list [one, two, also_one, also_two] has 4 valid arrangements that can result from being sorted.

Stable sort is sorting with the additional requirement that all elements that are equal will stay true to the relative ordering of the original list. This means that the list [one, two, also_one, also_two] only has one valid arrangement and that is [one, also_one, two, also_two] because one was originally in front of also_one and two was originally in front of also_two.

The sorting methods that we have looked at so far have all been stable sorts, but must of them do have unstable counterparts.

sort --> sort_unstable
sort_by --> sort_unstable_by
sort_by_key --> sort_unstable_by_key

The benefits to using an unstable sorting method is that they tend to be faster than their stable sort counterparts. However, if you need to guarantee that there will only ever be one valid sorted arrangement, then you should us a stable sort.

Chapter 5: Common Uses For Sorting

Sorting is typcally done for two reasons: comparing and search. When comparing lists of elements, order matters because equality means that every element at each index is equal. For example, [1, 2, 3] is not equal to [2, 3, 1] even though they contain the same elements because the values at each index are not equal.

Example 5.1

let a = vec![1, 2, 3, 4];
let b = vec![2, 3, 1, 4];

println!("{:?} == {:?} => {}", a, b, a == b);

Output 5.1

[1, 2, 3, 4] == [2, 3, 1, 4] => false

However, if we sort both lists prior to checking for equality, we ensure that the elements of both lists have been ordered in the same manner. This gives us the expectation that, as long as both lists have the same elements, the sorted order of the list should be equal as well.

Example 5.2

let mut a = vec![1, 2, 3, 4];
let mut b = vec![2, 3, 1, 4];

a.sort();
b.sort();

println!("{:?} == {:?} => {}", a, b, a == b);

Output 5.2

[1, 2, 3, 4] == [1, 2, 3, 4] => true

When we talk about search, we are usually are talking about searching for an element from a collection of elements via a specific criteria. For example, given the list [2, 9, 3, 1, 8, 7, 6, 9, 0], asking if the number 5 is in the list is single element search.

Sorting makes searching easier because, if your collection of elements are sorted, then you know that you can leverage the rules of the logical arrangement to reach your answer faster. For example, sorting [2, 9, 3, 1, 8, 7, 6, 9, 0] in ascending order gives us [0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 7, 8, 9]. If we want to check if the number 5 is in the list, we now have a few ways we can go about it. A method that would work on both the sorted and unsorted version of the list is the brute force method where we look at every element of the list, starting from the left side and going right, and check if they are equal to 5. For an unsorted list, this makes sense because there is always the possibility that the next element in the list is 5. For a sorted list, this seems silly because you end up doing a number of unnecessary checks. For example, if you start from the left most element, which is 0, and move right, you will eventually reach the number 6. Sorting in acending order means that every number to the right of 6 are equal to or greater than 6, which means that 5 cannot be to the right of 6. Stopping our search here would save us 3 comparisions (7, 8, 9).

If we stared from the right most element, which is the number 9, and moved left, we would eventually reach the number 4. Ascending order also mean that all the elements to the left of 4 are equal to or less than 4, which means that 5 cannot be to the left of 4. Stopping our search here would save us 4 comparisons (0, 1, 2, 3).

Given how much the rules of ascending order tells us about the list, there is no harm in starting our search from an arbitrary location. For example, if we started our search in th middle of the list, which is at number 4, we know that if the number 5 is in the list, then it would be to the right of number 4, This means that our search algorithm now knows what direction to continue its search in. If we were to repeat these steps on the sublist that is [6, 7, 8, 9], we see that 7 is the new middle element. We know that 7 is greater than 5 and that everything to the right of 7 is also greater than 5, so we create a new sublist that is [6]. There is only one element in this sublist and it is the number 6, which is also greater than 5. At this point, after 3 comparisons, we can conclude that 5 is not in the list. This technique is called binary search because, for each search attempt, it allows us to create a new sublist that consists of half the number of elements of the previous sublist to search through. Though binary search it a powerful searching technique, I want to point out that we were only able to use it because we understood how the list was ordered.

Sorting elements in ascending order makes sense because it is a widely understood logical arrangment of elements, but, depending on your searching criteria and history, it may not be the best ordering for you. For example, if you have a list of elements and you know that you tend to search for a certain subset of these elements more often than others, why not sort your list into a different logical arrangment that makes finding the elements that you commonly search for easier? If you tend to search for the number 5 in a list, why not prioritize 5 and put it at the beginning of the sorted list? Or, if you know that you search for odd numbers more than even numbers, why not sort your list so that all the odd numbers are before all the even numbers and both groups of numbers are in ascending order? With these logical arrangments, you will have an easier time finding the elements you tend to search. All in all, I want us remember that we sort elements into a logical arrangements of elements to make the process of achieving our goal easier and that we have control over which logical arrangement we choose to use.

Chapter 10: Poker Hands

We have learned how to sort lists of items into a single logical arrangement. Admittedly, this covers the practical cases of sorting. Moving towards the impractical, let's explore how we handle sorting into more than one logical arrangement.

Poker is a great example of this because, when we compare poker hands, we need to be able to sort the hand so that all the high value cards are in the front. The poker hand type dictates the logical arrangement that your sort needs to adhere to. Below is a list of the poker hands.

Poker Hands

Royal Flush

10 to Ace, all the same suit

Straight Flush

Five cards of the same suit in sequential order

Four of a Kind

Four cards with the same rank

Full House

Three of a Kind and One Pair

Flush

Five cards of the same suit

Straight

Five cards of any suit in sequential order

Three of a Kind

Three cards with the same rank

Two Pair

Two sets of One Pair

One Pair

Two cards with the same rank

High Card

The card with the highest rank

If we had a One Pair poker hand of <3, 2, 1, 5, 2>, we would want to sort our hand so that the pair is at the front of the list, followed by the rest of the cards in high card order (descending order based on card rank -- <2, 2, 5, 3, 1>). This ordering makes it easy to compare One Pair hands. For example, if hand one is <2, 2, 5, 3 ,1> and hand two is <6, 6, 3, 2, 1>. We can compare each card in the hands from left to right and know which hand is greater. This technique works even when two hands have the same pair; <2, 2, 5, 3, 1> vs <2, 2, 6, 4, 1>.

If we had a High Card poker hand, then we would want to sort our cards solely by our high cards. So a High Card sort of <4, 8, J, A, 5> would become <A, J, 8, 5, 4>. Based on these examples, we see that our sorting function is dictated by the type of poker hand we have.

Creating Cards

In order to create poker hands, we first need to create cards to play with.

Example 10.1

#[derive(Debug)]
enum Suit {
    Heart,
    Club,
    Spade,
    Diamond,
}

struct Card {
    rank: u8,
    suit: Suit,
}

fn main(){}

In our example, we created a Card struct that has two fields; rank and suit. The rank field is of type u8 and represents the Rank of the card. The suit field is a Suit Enum that have four variants; Heart, Club, Spade, and Diamond.

To make the cards visually less confusing, we are going to implement the Debug Trait and make sure that the numbeers 11 - 14 show J (Jack) Q (Queen), K (King) and A (Ace).

Example 10.2

use std::fmt;

...
		     
impl fmt::Debug for Card {
    fn fmt(&self, f: &mut fmt::Formatter<'_>) -> fmt::Result {
	let rank = match self.rank {
	    x @ 2 ..=10 => x.to_string(),
	    11 => "J".to_string(),
	    12 => "Q".to_string(),
	    13 => "K".to_string(),
	    14 => "A".to_string(),
	    _ => panic!("number {:?} is not a valid card number", &self.rank),
	};

	f.debug_struct("Card")
	    .field("rank", &rank)
	    .field("suit", &self.suit)
	    .finish()
    }
}

In our fmt method, we used a match statement on the Card.rank field to create our wanted string representations for the card's rank. If the value of the Card.rank is between 2 and 10, then we will convert them number to a string. We accomplished this by using the @ symbol in our match statement. The code x @ 2 ..= 10 allows us to check if the value of Card.rank is in the range of 2 ..= 10 and, if so, bind that value to x. Once that value has been bound to x, we use the match arm to convert x into a string and return it. If the value of Card.rank is 11, 12, 13 or 14, it will match with its own arm that will map it to a specific string representation. All other values, which are not valid ranks for poker, will be caught by the _ case and raise an error. After we have our local representation of our card's rank, we pass it to the formatter to be displayed.

Please note that our Card Debug implementation passes Card.suit to the formatter, which means that our Suit Enum needs to implement Debug for our Card Debug implementation to work. This is done by using derive to generate the debug implementation for Suit Enum.

Raising an error when we are trying to print the debug representation for our Card does not seem ideal. To prevent this from happening, we will create an associative function called new that will be responsible for creating our Cards. This function will verify that the value passed in for Card.rank is within in the range of 2 - 14 prior to creating the Card.

Example 10.3

...
		    
impl Card {
    fn new(rank: u8, suit: Suit) -> Result<Self, &'static str> {
        match rank {
            x @ 2..=14 => Ok(Card { rank: x, suit }),
            _ => Err("name must be in the range of 2 - 14"),
        }
    }
}

fn main() {
    for rank in 2..=14 {
        println!("{:?}", Card::new(rank, Suit::Heart).unwrap());
    }
}

Output 10.3

Card { rank: "2", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "3", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "4", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "5", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "6", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "7", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "8", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "9", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "10", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "J", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "Q", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "K", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "A", suit: Heart }

Our Card::new functionr returns a Result Enum, which has two variants; Ok and Err. If we are able to create a valid Card, we return a new Card instance wrapped in an Ok. If we are unable to create a valid Card, we return an Err with a message explaining what went wrong. To demonstrate the happy path, we updated the main function to print out all of the cards for a single suit. Now that we can create Cards, we need to implement the Ord Trait so that we can sort our cards.

In poker, we know that a card's suit only matters when the poker hand type says it matters. Since a card's suit does not always matter, we do not want to consider it during our default sorting process. This means that we have to manually implement our traits because deriving them would result in our Cards being sorted by rank and then by suit, when we only only want our cards sorted by rank.

Example 10.4

...
use std::cmp::Ordering;
		    
...

impl PartialEq for Card {
    fn eq(&self, other: &Self) -> bool {
        self.rank == other.rank
    }
}

impl Eq for Card {}

impl PartialOrd for Card {
    fn partial_cmp(&self, other: &Self) -> Option<Ordering> {
        Some(self.cmp(&other))
    }
}

impl Ord for Card {
    fn cmp(&self, other: &Self) -> Ordering {
        self.rank.cmp(&other.rank).reverse()
    }
}

fn main() {
    let mut cards = Vec::new();
    for rank in 2..=14 {
        cards.push(Card::new(rank, Suit::Heart).unwrap());
    }

    cards.sort();
    for card in cards{
	println!("{:?}", card);
    }
}

Output 10.4

Card { rank: "A", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "K", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "Q", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "J", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "10", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "9", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "8", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "7", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "6", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "5", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "4", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "3", suit: Heart }
Card { rank: "2", suit: Heart }

Now that we have implemented the Ord Trait, we now have the ability to sort a list of Cards. Please note that the cmp function uses the reverse method after comparing the name fields to make sure that the highest values get placed in front of the sorted list. To demonstrate the sorted order, we updated the main function to put the cards we created into a list, call sort on the list and then print out the items of the list.

Chapter 10: Poker - Sorting Strategies

As mentioned, the strategy used to sort our poker hand depends on the type of poker hand we have. For simplicity, we will assume that we have a 5 card hand. With this in mind, we can categories pocker hands into the following groups

Sort by Card Name

Technically speaking, High Card and Straight are the only poker hand in this category because they are the only hands judge solely by card rank. That said, sorting by card rank is the secondary sort for most poker hands. For example, if you sre comparing One Pair poker hands and both hands have a pair of aces, you wil have to look at the rest of the cards in both hands to determine the winner.

Sort by Card Rank and Suite

Royal Flush, Straight Flush and Flush can all be sorted by card rank while giving priority to a sing suite. If you only have 5 cards in your hand like we do, then you can ignore the suite because all 5 cards have the same suite which means that we no longer have to worry about prioritizing the suite. As a result, we can use the "Sort by Card Rank" to sort these hands.

Note: For the poker hands Straight and Straight Flush, we do have an edge case involving our Ace. An Ace can be at the front of the Straight [A, K, Q, J, 10] or at the end of a Straught [5, 4, 3, 2, A]. Since our Ace has a Card Rank of 14, it will naturally moved towards the front of the list. This means that post sorting, we have to manually check for the edge case where the Ace should be at the end of the list and move it there.

Sort by Card Rank with Priority to a Single Card Rank

Two Pair, Three Pair and Four of a Kind are in the same category because they all prioritize a single Card Rank when sorting. Once all the cards with the prioritized Card Rank are placed in the front of the list, the rest of the cards get sorted by High Card.

Sort by Card Rank while prioritizing 2 Card Ranks (Order Matters)

This sort is specifically for the poker hand Full House. A Full Houe is when you have Three of a kind and One Pair in the same hand. To sort this hand, we want to prioritize the Three of a Kind over the One Pair. This means that we have to indentify which card rank is associated with the Three of a Kind and make sure that we prioritize that card rank over the one that is associated with the One Pair.

PokerHand

A couple things you may have noticed when listing out the sorting strategies for the poker hands is that most of these sorting strategies depend on extra information. Mainly, we need to know what Poker Hand Type we have and which Card Ranks we need to prioritize. So lets start ourlining our code

Our PokerHand Struct needs to hold a hand of cards and it needs to have a place to store its Poker Hand Type.

#[derive(Debug, Ord, PartialOrd, Eq, PartialEq)]
enum PokerHandType {
    RoyalFlush,
    StraightFlush,
    FourOfAKind,
    FullHouse,
    Flush,
    Straight,
    ThreeOfAKind,
    TwoPair,
    Pair,
    HighCard,
}

#[derive(Debug)]
struct PokerHand {
    cards: Vec<Card>,
    poker_hand_type: Option<PokerHandType>,
}

impl PokerHand {
	def new() -> Self {
		PokerHand{cards: Vec::new(), poker_hand_type: None}
	}
}

In our code, we made the PokerHandType an enum where the variants are the different poker hands. We also order the poker hand variants from the best to the worst. We did this so that we can use the derived implementations of Ord Trait and all the other Traits needed to implement the Ord Trait. This is our first time doing this with Enums, but it works the same way as it does with Structs. This means we can now compare and sort the varaints of our PokerHandType enum and, because we defined them in the order of strongest hand to weakest hand, the sorted list will place the strongest hands in front of the weaker ones.

For our PokerHand Struct, we have our Vector of Cards and a Optional PokerHandType Enum. The PokerHandType is optional because it should only be deduced after we have all five Cards in our hand. With that in mind, lets create functions and methods for our PokerHand Struct that allow us to create a new hand and add cards to it.

impl PokerHand {
    fn new() -> Self {
        PokerHand {
            cards: Vec::new(),
            poker_hand_type: None,
        }
    }

    fn add_card(&mut self, card: Card) -> Result<(), &'static str> {
        // Our card hand limit is 5.
        if self.cards.len() == 5 {
            return Err("Max hand limit is 5");
        }

        self.cards.push(card);
        Ok(())
    }
}

Our name function creates an empty PokerHand with no cards and the poker_hand_type set to None. Our add_cards method allows us to add a Card to our PokerHand. This method returns a Result because our PokerHand has a 5 card limit. If we try to add a 6th card, we will raise an error.

Noe that we have the ability to add cards to our hand, lets move on to deducing our poker_hand_type. We can do this with three helper methods; card_rank_histogram, have_flush, and have_straight.

The card_rank_histogram method counts how many times each card rank is represented in our hand and returns a histogram in the form of a list of tuples where the tuple is (card_rank as u8, count as usize). This list will be returned sorted by count and the card rank in descending order. This means that if our hand is [1, 9, 1, 1, 1], we will get [(1, 4), (9, 1)].

The reason this histogram is important is because a number of poker hands are based on how many times a card rank is represented in your hand. For example,FourOfAKind, FullHouse, ThreeOfAKind, TwoPair and OnePair can all be deduced by looking at the first two entries of our histogram list (ie, the top two hightest represented card ranks in our hand).

The have_flush and have_straight methods return a boolean. They are used to deduce all other poker hand types. For example, if you have a flush and a stright, then we must look at your cards because you could have a RoyalFlush, StriaghtFlush or a Flush. If you do not have a Flush, but you have a straight, then you have a Straight. If you do not have a Flush or a Straight, then you have a HighCard hand.

fn card_rank_histogram(&self) -> Vec<(u8, usize)> {
    let mut map = HashMap::new();

    for card in &self.cards {
        map.entry(card.name)
            .and_modify(|count| *count += 1)
            .or_insert(1);
    }

    let mut results: Vec<(u8, usize)> = map
        .iter()
        .map(|(k, v)| (k.clone(), v.clone() as usize))
        .collect();
    results.sort_by(|a, b| a.1.cmp(&b.1).then(a.0.cmp(&b.0)).reverse());

    results
}

The card_rank_histogram code uses a HashMap to get a count of the card ranks. The HashMap Entry API allows us to do the counting logic and add entries into the HashMap in one line. map.entry(card.rank) is the starting point to the Entry API. This call returns an Entry Enum Variant that is either Occupied or Vacant. If the card.rank exists in the HashMap, map.entry will return Entry::Occupied. The Entry::Occupied enum variant has code for the and_modify method that will take the value assciated with this key and pass it to the anonymous function passed to the and_modify method. We then take this value, which represents our count and then add one to it.

If card.rank does not exist in the hashmap, map.entry will return Entry::Vacant. The Entry::Vacant enum variant has code for the or_insert(1) method that will add card.rank to the HashMap as a new entry and set the value to 1.

The confusing part about the Entry API is that it leaverages No-Op (no operation_ calls to work. For example, the or_insert method is called on the Entry::Occupied enum variant, but it has not effect because it is a No-Op call. The same is true for calling the and_modify method on the Entry::Vacant enum variant. So, in order to understand what the code is doing, you have to think about that happens in both cases. If it is the first time the HashMap ha seen this card rank, we give it a count of 1. If it is not the first time we have seen this card rank, we take its current count and add 1 to it.

The next part of the code uses iterators to convert the HashMap into a Vector of Tuples. We do this via the map method, which give us access to the key values of the HashMap as a tuple. Not wanting to take ownership of these values, we clone and cast them them as needed to get the type we want. We then use the collect method to place out tuples in a Vector. We do this by explicitly stating the type of our variable (let mut results: Vec<(u8, usize)> = ...).

Once we have our list, we sort it by the count (tuple index 1_ and then card rank (tuple index 0). Calling reverse on the end of the compare chain ensures that the largest values will be at the beginning of the list, which gives us descending order.

fn have_flush(&self) -> bool {
    let mut result = true;

    let suite = &self.cards[0].suite;
    for card in &self.cards[1..] {
        if card.suite != *suite {
            result = false;
            break;
        }
    }

    result
}

The has_flush code is straight forward in the sense that we look at the suite of the first card in the list and then check to see if the rest of the cards in the list have the same suite. If so, we have a Flush and return true. Otherwise we return false.

fn have_straight(&self) -> bool {
    let mut ranks: Vec<u8> = self.cards.iter().map(|card| card.name.clone()).collect();

    ranks.sort();

    if ranks == [2, 3, 4, 5, 14] {
        true
    } else {
        let mut result = true;

	    let mut expected = ranks[0];
        for num in ranks {
            if num != expected {
                result = false;
                break;
            }

        expected += 1
        }

    result
    }
}

The have_straight code starts off by creating a mutable list of card ranks. We do this so that we can sort them because, in theory, to have a straight means that your first rank in the list is your starting point and every rank after it should be +1 of the prevous rank. the exception to this rule is when your striaght starts at the Ace ([A, 2, 3, 4, 5]). In that case, your sorted lidt would be [2, 3, 4, 5, 14]. In the code, we explicitly check for this case to make sure it gets handle and, for all other cases, we use our "in thoery" logic to check if the hand has a straight.

Now that we have all of the helper methods done, we can write the code to deduce and set our poker hand type.

    fn set_hand_type(&mut self) -> Result<(), &'static str> {
        if self.cards.len() != 5 {
            return Err("Must have 5 Cards to set hand type");
        }

        self.poker_hand_type = None;

        let card_rank_histogram = self.card_rank_histogram();

        // Check Poker hand Types that have multiple cards of the same rank
        if card_rank_histogram[0].1 == 4 {
            self.poker_hand_type = Some(PokerHandType::FourOfAKind);
        } else if card_rank_histogram[0].1 == 3 && card_rank_histogram[1].1 == 2 {
            self.poker_hand_type = Some(PokerHandType::FullHouse);
        } else if card_rank_histogram[0].1 == 3 && card_rank_histogram[1].1 == 1 {
            self.poker_hand_type = Some(PokerHandType::ThreeOfAKind);
        } else if card_rank_histogram[0].1 == 2 && card_rank_histogram[1].1 == 2 {
            self.poker_hand_type = Some(PokerHandType::TwoPair);
        } else if card_rank_histogram[0].1 == 2 && card_rank_histogram[1].1 == 1 {
            self.poker_hand_type = Some(PokerHandType::Pair)
        }

        // Check to see if we should return early
        if self.poker_hand_type.is_some() {
            return Ok(());
        }

        match (self.have_straight(), self.have_flush()) {
            (false, false) => self.poker_hand_type = Some(PokerHandType::HighCard),
            (false, true) => self.poker_hand_type = Some(PokerHandType::Flush),
            (true, false) => self.poker_hand_type = Some(PokerHandType::Straight),
            (true, true) => {
                let mut ranks: Vec<u8> = self.cards.iter().map(|card| card.name.clone()).collect();
                ranks.sort();
                if ranks[0] == 10 {
                    self.poker_hand_type = Some(PokerHandType::RoyalFlush);
                } else {
                    self.poker_hand_type = Some(PokerHandType::StraightFlush);
                }
            }
        }

        match self.poker_hand_type {
            None => Err("We unable to figure out your poker hand type"),
            Some(ref _hand_type) => Ok(()),
        }
    }

The set_hand method first checks to see if we have 5 cards in our hand. The is a mandatory step because our code was written the the assumption of our hands only having 5 cards. If we have more or less than 5 cards, the code will not work as expected.

Next, we set self.poker_hand_type to None. This is important because we will use this value to check to see if we should return early. For example,if self.poker_hand_type is set to Some, then we know that we have deduced our poker hand type and we have no need to run any more checks.

After that, we call our card_rank_histogram method to obtain the count of the card ranks which are ordered by count and then rank in descending order so that the largest values appear first in the tuple. Knowing this, we use the card rank histogram to check the cases for FourOfAKind, FullHouse, ThreeOfAKind, TwoPair and OnePair. If any of these cases are tru, we set self.poker_hand_type to te appropriate poker hand type.

At this point, we check to see if self.poker_hand_type is set. If so, we return early. If not, it means that we still need to check the other cases. The other cases are flushes and straights cases. We use a match statement to list out the cases of have_flush and have_straight. For each case, we set self.poker_hand_type appropriately.

By this point, we have checked all of the possible poker hand cases. In thoery, self.poker_hand_type should be set by now. However, there is always the possbility that some part of our code is not correct. As such, we end the methodby checking to see if self.poker_hand_type was set. If it was set, we return an Ok. If it was not set, we return an error.

Preface

This book is about sorting. I acknowledge that "sorting" means many things to many people. As a Software Engineer, I would define sorting as the act of placing a collection of items in order. For example, if I take the list of [4, 3, 5, 2, 1], the sorted order will be [1, 2, 3, 4, 5].

If you agree with this definition, I agree with you. If you disagree with this definition, I also agree with you. My issue with this definition is that it is both correct and misleading. It implies that "sorting" can only result in one definitive order, but what is "order"?

The American Heritage dictionary defines order as a condition of logical or comprehensible arrangement among the separate elements of a group.

This means that as long as the final arrangment of elements is logical or comprehensible, they are ordered. With that in mind, lists like [1, 2, 3, 4, 5] and [5, 4, 3, 2, 1] are sorted because both ascending and descending order of numbers are logical arrangments. The same thing can be said for the list [1, 3, 5, 2, 4]. It's sorted because the numbers are placed in ascending order where the odd numbers are placed in front of the even numbers, which is a logical arrangement.

When it comes to the word "order", the important part is the logical arrangement. For example, the list [3, 1, 2, 4, 5] could be unordered, or it could be sorted in ascending order where 3's are given priority and placed at the front of the list. The distinguishing feature between unordered and ordered is resproducibility. If you generate the list [3, 1, 2, 4, 5] on your first attempt, but re-running the code tends to generate different lists, then it is safe to say that this is not a logical arrangement and that your list is not sorted.

Throughout this book we will be examining sorting with respect to ordering. We will perform this examination in Rust. That said, the learnings and general takeaways discovered should be easily transferable to the language of your choice. WIth respect to Rust, we will learn how to leverage sorting to achieve a cerain logical arrangement or order, we will learn how to implement sorting for custom structs, and we will learn how to exend our sorting capabilities at runtime to allow for dynamic sorting.